<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Act for publishing his Majesties most gracious letter</title>
            <title>Proclamations. 1700-07-26</title>
            <author>Scotland. Privy Council.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92634</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S1429</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229978</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899387</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899387</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153312</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92634)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153312)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2358:30)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Act for publishing his Majesties most gracious letter</title>
                  <title>Proclamations. 1700-07-26</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Privy Council.</author>
                  <author>William III, King of England, 1650-1702.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>2 sheets ([3] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by the heirs and successors of Andrew Anderson, printer to the King's most excellent Majesty,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>At end of text: Given at our court at Loo, the 26th day of July 1700. And of our reign the 12th year.</note>
                  <note>With drop-head title on p.[2]: His Majesties most gracious letter: directed to his grace James Duke of Queensberry, his Majesties high commissioner, and the privy council of Scotland.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  1689-1714 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1689-1702 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  History --  1689-1745 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Politics and government --  1689-1745 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  Scotland</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:153312:1"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <head>W R</head>
                  <q xml:lang="frm">DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
                  <q xml:lang="frm">HONI SOIT QUI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                  <figDesc>English royal blazon, surmounted by a crown and flanked by the Scottish unicorn on one side and the English lion on the other</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>ACT For publiſhing His Majeſties moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Letter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>IS Majeſties high Commiſſioner, a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d Lords of His Majeſties Privy Council, having received from His Majeſty, the graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Letter ſubjoyned, with the Order therein contained; Appointing the ſame to be Publiſhed, for the Satisfaction of all His Majeſties good Subjects, do hereby Ordain the ſame to be publiſhed accordingly: And do therefore grant War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand, and Ordain His Majeſties Heraulds, Macers of Privy Council, Purſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, Meſſengers at Arms, to paſs to the Mercat-croſs of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and there make due Publication of the ſaid Letter with ſound of Trumpet, and all other Solemnities. And Further, Ordains the ſame to be Printed, and His Majeſties Solicitor to tranſmit Copies thereof, and of this Act, to the Sheriffs of the ſeveral Shires, and Stewarts of the Stewartries, their Deputs or Clerks, who are hereby<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> required to cauſe publiſh the ſame at the Head burghs of their reſpective J<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>iſdictions, after the Manner and Form of publick Proclamations, as they will be anſwerable.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Per Actum Dominorum Secreti Concilii. <hi>GILB. ELIOT.</hi> Cls. Sti. Concilii.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>Follows the Tenor of His Majeſties Letter.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:153312:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:153312:3"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>crown surmounting the French fleur-de-lis flanked by the Scottish thistle on one side and the Tudor rose on the other</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>His Majeſties MOST GRACIOUS LETTER: Directed to His Grace <hi>JAMES</hi> Duke of <hi>Queensberry,</hi> His Majeſties High Commiſſioner, and the Privy Council of <hi>SCOTLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <signed>WILLIAM R.</signed>
               <lb/>
               <salute>RIght Truſty and Intirely Beloved Couſin and Counſellor, Right <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ruſty and Right well Beloved Couſin and Counſellor, Right Truſty and well Beloved Couſins &amp; Counſellors, Right Truſty and well Beloved Counſellors, and Truſty and well Beloved Counſellors, We Greet you well.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>We heartily wiſh that the laſt Meeting of Parliament had proceeded, ſo as that the Kingdom might have been made Partakers of theſe Advantages for which Our Commiſſioner was ſo fully Inſtructed: If it had been poſſible for Us to have agreed to the <hi>Reſolve</hi> offered to Aſſert the Right of the <hi>African-Companies</hi> Colony in <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica,</hi> tho' that Method had appeared to Us more unneceſſary, yet We had from the beginning readily done it, at the earneſt Deſire of Our Miniſters, and for Our Peoples Satisfaction, all other Conſiderations ſet apart. But now that Things are much changed, (wherein We are truely Sorry for the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions Loſs) And We being moſt willing to Grant what may be needful for the Releif and Eaſe of the Kingdom, and the Advancement of its Welfare in all its Concerns: We have thought fit to Declare this Our good Mind to be made Known to all Our loving Subjects. And for the <hi>Companies</hi> Concerns, We Aſſure you, that We will be ſo ready to concur with Our Parliament, in every thing that can be reaſonably expected of Us, for Aiding &amp; Supporting their Intereſts, and Repairing their Loſſes, that Our good Subjects ſhall have juſt Grounds to be ſenſible of our heartie Inclinations to advance the Wealth and Proſperity of that our Antient Kingdom. And as for Captain <hi>Pinkerton</hi> and the other Priſoners in <hi>Spain,</hi> We have alreadie, and We hope Eſſectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Interpoſed for their Liberation. In the next place, As We did fully In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct our Commiſſioner, So We are ſtill Reſolved, to paſs all ſuch Laws as
<pb facs="tcp:153312:3"/> ſhall be offered for the better Eſtabliſhing the true Proteſtant Religion, and the Presbyterian Government of the Church, which you at preſent Enjoy; For the more effectual preventing the Growth of Popery juſtly feared, for the Repreſſing of Vice &amp; Immorality, for the Preſerving &amp; Securing the Liberty of Mens Perſons, for the Encouraging &amp; Advancement of Trade &amp; Manufacturies, and generally, to give Our Aſſent to ſuch other Laws as ſhall be brought in for further clearing and ſecuring Mens civil Rights and Properties, promoting the Adminiſtration of Juſtice, and ſetling the Peace and Quiet of the Kingdom, demanding nothing on Our part, ſave what ſhall be neceſſary to Maintain that Our antient Kingdom in ſo happy a Settlement againſt Our and Their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. And this Declaration, We are confident will be ſatisfying to all good Men, who will certainly be careful both of their own Preſervation, and of the Intereſt and Honour of the Government, and not to ſuffer themſelves to be Miſted, nor to give any Advantage to Enemies &amp; ill deſigning Perſons, ready to catch hold of every Opportunity, as their Practices do too manifeſtly wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>Our neceſſary Abſence hath occaſioned the late Adjournments, but as ſoon as God ſhall bring Us back, We are firmly Reſolved Our Parliament ſhall Meet, where We do again Aſſure all Our good Subjects, nothing ſhall be Wanting on Our part, that may contribute to their Welfare and Happineſs. And this Our Reſolution and Declaration, We Allow you to Publiſh for the Satisfaction of all concerned. So We bid you heartily Farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given at Our Court at <hi>Loo,</hi> 
                  <date>the 26th day of <hi>July</hi> 1700. And of Our Reign the 12th year.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>By His Majeſties Command, RO. PRINGLE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> Printed by the Heirs and Succeſſors of <hi>Andrew Anderſon,</hi> Printer to the King's moſt Excellent Majeſty, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1700.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:153312:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
